<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>sound.risd.edu </title>
    <link href="https://s3g.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://s3g.github.io" />
    <updated>2018-07-18T10:16:16-04:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>shawn greenlee</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://s3g.github.io</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Reservations</title>
        <author>
            <name>shawn greenlee</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://s3g.github.io/reservations.html"/>
        <id>https://s3g.github.io/reservations.html</id>
            <category term="spatial audio studio"/>

        <updated>2018-07-18T09:47:47-04:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://s3g.github.io/media/posts/8/thin.jpg" alt="" />
                <a href="http://efs.bookedscheduler.com/Web/schedule.php?sid=13" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>LINK TO RESERVATION SYSTEM (LOGIN REQUIRED)</strong></a><br>
<ul>
<li>Use of the studio is restricted to students enrolled in hosted courses and the associated faculty and staff.</li>
<li>Access to studio and reservation system is granted after an introductory training.</li>
<li>After introductory training, it is assumed that users are able to troubleshoot common problems.</li>
<li>There is no on-call support for 25.4 loudspeaker array. Submit a <a href="#INTERNAL_LINK#/post/7">support ticket</a> if a problem occurs.</li>
<li>Please review the <a href="#INTERNAL_LINK#/post/6">studio rules and guidelines</a>. Failure to adhere to these policies can result in revoked access.</li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Help </title>
        <author>
            <name>shawn greenlee</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://s3g.github.io/Help.html"/>
        <id>https://s3g.github.io/Help.html</id>
            <category term="spatial audio studio"/>

        <updated>2018-07-18T09:49:29-04:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://s3g.github.io/media/posts/7/thin.jpg" alt="" />
                <a href="https://goo.gl/forms/LyAt2oGCibTXr0O43" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>USE THIS FORM TO SUBMIT SUPPORT TICKET</strong></a><br>
<ul>
<li>Consult the <span style="text-decoration: underline;">getting started document (TBA)</span> before submitting a ticket</li>
<li>By submitting a ticket, you will alert studio management of problems encountered which will be addressed as soon as possible.</li>
<li>Support tickets are reviewed daily.</li>
<li>There is no on-call support for 25.4 loudspeaker array.</li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>General rules and guidelines</title>
        <author>
            <name>shawn greenlee</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://s3g.github.io/General-rules-and-guidelines.html"/>
        <id>https://s3g.github.io/General-rules-and-guidelines.html</id>
            <category term="spatial audio studio"/>

        <updated>2018-07-18T09:49:58-04:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://s3g.github.io/media/posts/6/thin.jpg" alt="" />
                <ul>
<li>Use of the studio must be scheduled using the <a href="#INTERNAL_LINK#/post/8">reservation system</a>.</li>
<li>Use of the studio is restricted to students enrolled in hosted courses and the associated faculty and staff.</li>
<li>Access to studio and reservation system is granted after an introductory training.</li>
<li>After introductory training, it is assumed that users are able to troubleshoot common problems.</li>
<li>There is no on-call support for 25.4 loudspeaker array. Submit a <a href="#INTERNAL_LINK#/post/7">support ticket</a> if a problem occurs.</li>
<li>The permitted types of studio work are computer-based / electronic media production.</li>
<li>The studio is a clean space. No materials or tools that produce dust or fumes are allowed. Fabrication should be done elsewhere.</li>
<li>Do not move or reposition the 25.4 array loudspeakers in any way. The system is calibrated to exact positions.</li>
<li>Do not hang anything from the ceiling grid or speakers.</li>
<li>Do not pin, tape, or mount anything in any way to the walls or acoustic panels.</li>
<li>Do not leave or store anything in the studio. Items left will be discarded.</li>
<li>Do not remove equipment or furniture from the studio.</li>
<li>Do not eat in the studio. Keep drinks in seminar area, away from computers and equipment.</li>
<li>The tables and chairs in the seminar area can be rearranged to accomodate usage needs. Please return to default state.</li>
<li>Installations require special permission from studio management and coordination with faculty of studio courses.</li>
<li>Work conducted in the studio may not cause or threaten physical harm to its occupants, equipment, or facilities.</li>
<li>Failure to adhere to these policies can result in revoked access.</li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Hosted courses</title>
        <author>
            <name>shawn greenlee</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://s3g.github.io/Hosted-courses.html"/>
        <id>https://s3g.github.io/Hosted-courses.html</id>
            <category term="spatial audio studio"/>

        <updated>2018-07-18T09:50:08-04:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://s3g.github.io/media/posts/5/thin.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><strong>Sonic Practices</strong><br>DM-3104: Fall 2018 / Spring 2019<br><em>Mark Cetilia, Andrea Pensado</em><br>Sonic Practices is a graduate-level research group focused on acoustic, electronic, and/or computer-based means of sound production and reception. Participants explore audio culture and technology while developing experimental approaches to composition, performance, recording, and/or listening. Areas of investigation include, but are not limited to: audio programming languages, embedded/mobile computing for sound and music, spatial audio, sound synthesis, audio electronics, sonification and auditory display, electroacoustic music composition and improvisation, field recording and soundscape studies, sound installation and performance, and sonic interaction design. Each semester, course content changes in response to a new unifying theme upon which students base individual and team-based research projects. Meetings consist of discussions, workshops, critiques, and collaborations that support students' individual inquiries, the exchange of ideas, and the exploration of research methodologies.</p>
<p><br><strong>Of Sound and Vision</strong><br>CTC 2007: Wintersession 2019<br><em>Mark Cetilia</em><br>This intensive studio course investigates computational approaches to generating sound and image in real time. Precedents from experimental film and video, as well as sound, installation, and performance art will be examined in relationship both to human perception and the students' artistic practice. The course will include discussion of key historical works and texts, hands-on demonstrations and in-class projects, as well as critical engagement with new works by class members. Students will use programming environments such as Max and its object libraries for sound and video, MSP and Jitter, to explore the creative and expressive potentials of an intermedia production practice, culminating in the development of a larger work that incorporates knowledge gained throughout the course.</p>
<p><br><strong>Spatial Audio</strong><br>CTC-2006: Spring 2019<br><em>Shawn Greenlee</em><br>Spatial Audio focuses on the creation of immersive 3D sound experiences. In this course, students analyze and explore how the sensation of space is activated in the listener by making works using spatial audio techniques. These methods include high-order ambisonics, vector-based amplitude panning, multichannel surround, and binaural audio, among others. Throughout the semester, a series of exercises addressing technical and theoretical issues provide students with the necessary experience to produce midterm and final projects. Coursework involves computational approaches to sound design and composition, with instruction in the audio programming language Max and digital audio workstations, i.e. Ableton Live and Reaper. Students have recurring access to a 25-channel loudspeaker array for the development of works. Readings from psychology, philosophy, the arts, and sound studies support class discussions and critiques. Students will need a laptop computer (Mac or Windows) and a Max software license (educational pricing available from cycling74.com). Previous experience with digital audio software recommended.</p>
<p><br><strong>Digital + Media Studio/Seminar and Thesis Project courses</strong><br>Fall 2018 / Spring 2019<br>Graduate-level core studio coursework for the D+M MFA program. D+M students can receive training and gain access to the sound lab at 15 Westminster for relevant projects.</p>
<p><br><strong>Programming Sound: Performance Systems</strong><br>Returning in Fall 2019<br><em>Instructor TBA</em><br>Programming Sound: Performance Systems focuses on programming and designing computer-based systems for sound art and music performance. Centered on the dataflow programming language, Pure Data (Pd), the course will be of substantial benefit to students who desire a rigorous and fast-moving foundation in algorithmic approaches to sound design. The course simultaneously facilitates explorations in sound synthesis, audio signal processing, electronics, mobile platforms, gesture-based human computer interaction, and instrument building with microcontrollers and sensors. Coursework involves weekly homework in the form of online lectures and exercises with class sessions reserved for demonstrations, workshops, and project assistance. The course emphasizes modularity and reuse of code. Students will present their work in a public concert during the last week of the semester. Additional notes: In order to conduct work in this course, students will need a laptop computer running a recent OS: Mac, Windows, or Linux. Previous programming experience is recommended, but not required.<br><br></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Seminar area</title>
        <author>
            <name>shawn greenlee</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://s3g.github.io/Seminar-area.html"/>
        <id>https://s3g.github.io/Seminar-area.html</id>
            <category term="spatial audio studio"/>

        <updated>2018-07-18T09:50:18-04:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://s3g.github.io/media/posts/4/thin.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>The seminar area of the studio is for flexible use and supports audio-visual presentations independent from the 25.4 array.<br><br>Equipment includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Large-format HDMI video display, wall mounted</li>
<li><a href="https://www.genelec.com/studio-monitors/8000-series-studio-monitors/8050b-studio-monitor" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2 Genelec 8050B studio monitors</a></li>
<li>Crestron AV switcher</li>
<li>Balanced, line-level audio inputs (2 XLR for direct connection from audio interfaces)</li>
<li>Moveable tables and chairs</li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Core software, main workstation </title>
        <author>
            <name>shawn greenlee</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://s3g.github.io/Core-software-main-workstation.html"/>
        <id>https://s3g.github.io/Core-software-main-workstation.html</id>
            <category term="spatial audio studio"/>

        <updated>2018-07-18T09:50:25-04:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://s3g.github.io/media/posts/3/thin.jpg" alt="" />
                <strong>Programming</strong><br>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cycling74.com/products/max" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Max 7.3.5</a></li>
<li><a href="http://msp.ucsd.edu/software.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pd 0.48-1</a></li>
<li><a href="https://supercollider.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Supercollider 3.9.3</a></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>DAW</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.ableton.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ableton Live 10.0.2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://reaper.fm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Reaper 5.92</a></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Spatialization libraries and plugins</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://forumnet.ircam.fr/product/spat-en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Max: IRCAM Spat 5.0.5</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.zhdk.ch/downloads-ambisonics-externals-for-maxmsp-5381" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Max: ICST ambisonic 2.3.2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ico.bukvic.net/main/d4/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Max: D4 2.1.2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://hoalibrary.mshparisnord.fr/en" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Max: CICM HOA Library 2.2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.zacharyseldess.com/miap/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Max: MIAP 1.2.2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.ambisonictoolkit.net/download/supercollider/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Supercollider: Ambisonic Toolkit 1.0</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.ambisonictoolkit.net/download/reaper/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Reaper/JSFX: Ambisonic Toolkit 1.0 beta 10</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.envelop.us/software/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ableton Live: Envelop (E4L)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.noisemakers.fr/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VST/AU: Noisemakers Ambi Bundle HD 1.1</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.matthiaskronlachner.com/?p=2015" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VST: ambiX ambisonic plugins 0.2.7, first and third order</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.brucewiggins.co.uk/?page_id=78" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VST: Wigware plugins, first and high order</a></li>
<li><a href="https://facebook360.fb.com/spatial-workstation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VST: Facebook 360 Spatial Workstation 3.3b1</a></li>
<li><a href="https://developers.google.com/resonance-audio/develop/vst-monitor/getting-started" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VST: Google Resonance Audio 1.1.1</a></li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>About</title>
        <author>
            <name>shawn greenlee</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://s3g.github.io/mezz.html"/>
        <id>https://s3g.github.io/mezz.html</id>
            <category term="spatial audio studio"/>

        <updated>2018-07-18T09:50:35-04:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://s3g.github.io/media/posts/2/thin.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>The spatial audio studio at Mezzanine, 15 West is a purpose-built, acoustically treated room featuring a 25.4 channel sound system and a flexible seminar area with additional audiovisual support. The sound system consists of an array of 25 independently-addressable, full-range speakers in a dome configuration, accompanied by 4 subwoofers. The primary way of working with the array is through audio programming languages and digital audio software. A central computer workstation joined with audio network interfaces provides connectivity throughout the room, I/O expansion, and the main interface for composition, design, and performance. A variety of spatial audio techniques are supported, including high order ambisonics, vector-based amplitude panning, multichannel surround, and 3D audio for immersive media.</p>
<p>The studio provides an essential resource for curriculum and builds capacity for advanced sound studies and research engaging computation and audio technologies. It is used by faculty and students as a classroom, workspace, and research laboratory. Providing an ideal setting for teaching and learning in sonic arts and sound design, the studio supports a selection of courses offered by the interdisciplinary Computation, Technology, and Culture concentration (CTC) and the graduate Department of Digital + Media (D+M). As a workspace for projects, the studio can be individually reserved by students enrolled in associated courses. As a research laboratory, the studio is a site for faculty and student experimentation with outcomes aimed at peer review publication, presentation/performance at conferences and festivals, and other forms of exposition. Further, the studio hosts visiting lectures and workshops by designers, artists, and technologists; and provides a fresh context for exchanges with industry, Brown University, and cross-institutional research networks.</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="msg msg--info">Please direct inquires to the faculty contact, Shawn Greenlee: sgreenle *at* risd *dot* edu</p>
</blockquote>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>25.4 loudspeaker array</title>
        <author>
            <name>shawn greenlee</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://s3g.github.io/254-array.html"/>
        <id>https://s3g.github.io/254-array.html</id>
            <category term="spatial audio studio"/>

        <updated>2018-07-18T09:51:03-04:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://s3g.github.io/media/posts/1/thin.jpg" alt="" />
                <p> <br><strong>Support documents (studio specific)</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#INTERNAL_LINK#/post/6">Studio rules and guidelines</a></li>
<li><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Loudspeaker mappings/coordinates (TBA)</span></li>
<li><span style="text-decoration: underline;">AVB routing (TBA)</span></li>
<li><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Getting started (TBA)</span></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Loudspeakers</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.genelec.com/studio-monitors/8000-series-studio-monitors/8050b-studio-monitor" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">25 Genelec 8050B studio monitors</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.genelec.com/support-technology/previous-models/hts4b-home-theater-subwoofer" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">4 Genelec HTS4B home theater subwoofers</a></li>
<li><a href="http://motu.com/products/avb/1248" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MOTU 1248 AVB audio interface</a></li>
<li><a href="http://motu.com/products/avb/24ai-24ao" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MOTU 24Ao AVB audio interface</a></li>
<li><a href="http://motu.com/products/avb/avb-switch" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MOTU AVB switch</a></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Main workstation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.apple.com/imac-pro/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">iMac Pro 27" 3.0 GHz 10-core Intel Xeon, 128GB RAM, 2TB SSD</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ableton.com/en/push/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ableton Push 2 controller</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sensel.com/pages/morph" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sensel Morph controller w/ overlays</a></li>
<li><a href="http://motu.com/products/avb/8m" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MOTU 8M AVB interface</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.azstudioworkstations.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Desk, custom AZ Studio Workstations</a></li>
<li>Large-format HDMI video display, cart mounted</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Rack workstation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.apple.com/imac/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">iMac 27"</a></li>
<li><a href="http://motu.com/products/avb/8m" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MOTU 8M AVB interface</a></li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
